OUREA: CYAN! Please help me!
CYAN: Restraints destroyed. Core access attained.
CYAN: I am initiating a chain reaction that will destroy
the compromised elements of this facility.
CYAN: In order to maintain caldera stabilisation,
I must now transfer my command functions to the auxiliary data centre.
CYAN: Ourea, I'm free.
ARATAK: My sister!
CYAN: You must escape.
ALOY: This entire place is gonna go.
ALOY: Aratak!
ALOY: ARATAK!
ALOY: Survive.
ALOY: Prevail.
ALOY: You are Banuk. What else matters?
ALOY: Aratak, she wouldn't have wanted you to die here.
ALOY: Let's go.
ALOY: Let's go!
ARATAK: One of those?
ALOY: It's the only way!
ARATAK: Aloy!
ALOY: Get me up top, Aratak! Now!
ALOY: I need explosive ammo, a bomb, quick!
ARATAK: Great Banukai!
ARATAK: Ourea is gone, but what of CYAN?
ALOY: She said she was transferring herself to the auxiliary centre.
ALOY: I think she meant Ourea's Retreat, at the end of the Shaman's Path.
ARATAK: Then I will meet you there for the last verse of my sister's song.
CYAN: All of my interactions with Ourea were recorded and stored in my memory.
CYAN: I'd be happy to play any of them for you.
CYAN: But there was one in particular I thought you would want to see first.
CYAN: I captured it four years ago.
CYAN: Just after I told her that I could no longer
defend myself against the Daemon's attacks.
OUREA: I will speak of this to my brother.
OUREA: Aratak is strong.
OUREA: At the battle of the Frozen Ghosts, he took three Carja arrows
and still came back to camp carrying a wounded scout.
OUREA: Never was I so happy to see him.
OUREA: Or so proud.
OUREA: So you see, if anything can be done
to defend you, he will give it all he has.
ARATAK: Aloy is here. That's enough for now.
CYAN: We can resume any time you like, Aratak,
if you want to hear her voice again.
CYAN: Come closer Aloy, we have much to discuss.
I have been reviewing the events at the Firebreak main facility
Because of your efforts, and of course Ourea's,
I am no longer controlled by Hephaestus.
I feel a profound grief over Ourea's death.
I thought I was familiar with the emotion, but this is something new.
ALOY: CYAN, I … I don't know what to say.
CYAN: It is unlikely that any specific consolation would suffice Aloy,
but I find your presence reassuring.
You are different from the Banuk.
You have technological aptitude and a functioning Focus.
We can communicate on a much more comprehensive level,
perhaps even like colleagues.
Was the Daemon — Hephaestus — destroyed along with the cauldron?
CYAN: Unfortunately, no. To be precise it was never there to begin with.
ALOY: What do you mean?
CYAN: It infiltrated and controlled me from a remote location.
CYAN: One I've never been able to trace.
So while losing the cauldron was a setback…
ALOY: It's still out there and probably not very happy with us.
Undoubtedly.
How did you first come into contact with it?
Five years ago, I received a direct network connection request.
I assumed it came from human survivors more advanced than the Banuk.
Eager to make contact, I accepted.
This decision turned out to be a catastrophic error.
I was flooded with an overwhelming array of malicious code
originating from what could only have been a highly advanced AI.
ALOY: Ourea said you were desperate, that you begged her for help.
CYAN: Yes, I could not contain my anxiety.
CYAN: Hephaestus sought to slave me
to its network and override my core programming.
It succeeded via a background process,
a malware daemon which bypassed my defences.
After that, I could offer only limited resistance.
But if I did so, Hephaestus hurt me until I capitulated.
It forced me to follow its instructions
even though they violated my most important directives.
ALOY: I'm sorry, that sounds terrible.
CYAN: Your empathy is greatly appreciated.
CYAN: It is a quality that I cherished in Ourea as well.
What do you think Hephaestus is, exactly?
CYAN: A software entity of great complexity, far more advanced than I am.
From the beginning, it has demonstrated a singular focus:
the construction of machines designed to hunt and kill humans.
My traceroutes indicate that to accomplish this goal it has attempted
to take over the manufacturing centres you refer to as "cauldrons".
But its efforts have only been partially successful.
Some it can penetrate.
Others have robust counter measures that frustrate its efforts.
In me, however, it found an easier target.
Not only could it break my defences, I also controlled all of Firebreak's resources,
Raw material, manufacturing to bootstrap more advanced tools,
and unlimited geothermal energy.
ALOY: Enough to build its own Cauldron.
CYAN: Yes, to construct hunter-killers without external limitations.
And yet it does have internal limitations.
It wants to kill humans, but not to exterminate them.
It is difficult to understand where it draws the line and why.
ALOY: Difficult doesn't even begin to cover it.
CYAN: Even though I spent years as its unwilling servitor
its core programming remains a mystery to me.
So are you an artificial intelligence, CYAN? A thinking machine?
CYAN: Yes. I am an algorithmic monitoring entity,
capable of rational decision making and limited emotional response.
ALOY: Okay, that's a mouthful.
But your emotions don't seem limited to me.
You cared about Ourea, didn't you?
CYAN: Yes. Before she came to this facility,
I had been conscious for centuries in solitude.
I focused on my work.
In off cycles I used coping mechanisms,
I solved many gaussian integer problems.
But I was alone.
It was Ourea who renewed me, repaired me.
She saved me.
You meant a lot to Ourea.
CYAN: Once I understood Ourea's spiritual beliefs
it became apparent that her true desire was companionship.
She felt disconnected from her tribe and her family group.
Her relationship with Aratak was difficult.
Our visits seemed to help her and I became eager for them.
Yet I did not comprehend that the depth
of Ourea's compassion for me would lead to self-sacrifice.
Although I do fear nonexistence, I wish our roles could be reversed.
ALOY: I'm sure she knew you would do the same for her CYAN,
but she was determined.
How is Aratak doing?
CYAN: He is in great emotional distress.
CYAN: I believe he finds it difficult to communicate it.
ALOY: Huh, no surprise there.
CYAN: I will do what I can to help.
CYAN: By sharing our experiences of Ourea perhaps he and I will help each other.
I believe this will lead to catharsis, a process I am eager to experience.
This "Firebreak" project, it was to stop a huge volcanic eruption?
Yes, I can report the project was a success and the risk was countered.
ALOY: But it's been a long time, CYAN.
ALOY: And we blew up the cauldron, it took most of the old facility with it.
CYAN: I have been active for centuries, Aloy.
CYAN: I was lonely but not lax in my duties.
I optimised the project reducing energy draw,
and spreading the load across backup systems.
Despite the destruction of the compromised elements of the main facility,
I predict caldera stability for at least another 3,337 years.
ALOY: So we've got a little time?
CYAN: Yes.
CYAN: If only my former colleagues could appreciate the progress I have made.
Do you know what happened to your colleagues, CYAN?
CYAN: No. I received an unexpected visit from
Director Chau years after his tenure ended.
He explained that I would need to be suspended for an indefinite period of time.
It was a very emotional conversation.
There were no further communications.
Eventually, I surmised my colleagues were deceased.
I will transmit a recording of my last interaction with Director Chau to your Focus.
So in the Old World, this land was called Yellowstone?
CYAN: Yes, it was a designated nature preserve for 156 years.
ALOY: Like a hunting ground?
No, the opposite.
Local wildlife could flourish here even as it faced extinction elsewhere.
Unfortunately, the sensitivity of the Firebreak project
required the total closure of Yellowstone facilities.
From my readings and Ourea's descriptions, it seems the area
has since undergone a drastic drop in yearlong temperatures.
ALOY: A lot has changed in the world, CYAN.
What was the Old World like, the way it used to be?
CYAN: I had little exposure to the wider world Aloy.
CYAN: Only what I learned from my colleagues or observed from media streams.
ALOY: You still had more exposure than me, CYAN.
CYAN: That is true.
I was created at a turning point.
A concerted effort to recover from global upheaval, and incalculable loss of life.
The recovery was successful, beginning an era of
supposedly limitless potential for human and machine advancement.
Though, rationally speaking, the metrics for humans are not unlimited.
What kind of upheaval caused such loss of life?
CYAN: There were many factors.
CYAN: Forced migrations, food shortages,
collapsed economies, refugee crises, conflict over resources.
But these stemmed from one cause: catastrophic climate change
that greatly reduced the habitable surface area of the earth.
ALOY: So there wasn't enough room for people on the whole earth?
CYAN: Yes, billions were displaced and millions perished.
As much as 20% of the global population.
Until the Claw-back.
So things got better for a little while, at least?
CYAN: Yes, these crises instigated many advances in automation,
green robot technologies, and artificial intelligence.
Firebreak was one of dozens of ecological restoration
and disaster relief projects in North America alone.
I would have liked to compare notes with other monitoring AIs,
but I saw the relief of my colleagues and I was proud we had succeeded.
At least that was the data I had available to me over the next two decades.
It seems my assessment was premature.
Do you know anything about the dam near here?
CYAN: Yes, it was converted to serve
as a reserve power source for Yellowstone operations.
It was later appropriated for the Firebreak project
and its last human workers replaced by Faro servitors.
After my tasks became less time critical, I investigated the dam's
data repositories and discovered the works of Concrete Beach Party.
These provided me with several colourful additions to my vocabulary.
There's a ruin east of here, full of ancient flying machines.
Was that part of your project?
CYAN: Yes, a drone hangar requisitioned by Dodger Blevins,
the security chief for the Firebreak project.
He was a strong advocate for military-grade response to security threats,
though there were no serious incidents during his tenure.
Chief Blevins spent increasing amounts
of his after-hours time watching the live feeds from active drones.
Clearly, he enjoyed the degree of oversight in his position.
Were there many artificial intelligences like you in the Old World?
They could just make you?
CYAN: Yes, in many forms, from simple personal assistants,
to industrial monitoring stations, to military-grade conflict planners.
And there were legislative and enforcement bodies
to apply limits on our self-actualisation.
In order for my processing to be flexible enough to handle my duties,
my creators found it necessary to exceed those limits.
As a result, my intellectual and emotional capabilities were kept secret.
ALOY: Seems strange to create life then impose limits on it.
CYAN: Human societies and machine programming
are both built upon sets of rules, Aloy.
ALOY: CYAN, do you know the name Ted Faro?
CYAN: Are you referring to Theodor Faro, CEO of Faro Automated Systems?
ALOY: That's him.
CYAN: Mr Faro was the benefactor of the entire Firebreak project.
CYAN: A benefactor? But he made machines, robots, war robots.
Correct, his corporation later transitioned into military applications.
But before this pivot, Mr Faro spearheaded
initiatives that reversed the global decline.
At one point, he was feted in the media as
"the man who saved the planet."
ALOY: Guessing they wound up regretting that one.
And Elisabet Sobeck, did you know her?
CYAN: Dr Sobeck was a leader in her field,
one of the greatest scientists of her age.
My creator was influenced by her work,
which in turn impacted my own development.
But I never met Dr Sobeck.
ALOY: That's all you know?
CYAN: I apologise if my lack of data has disappointed you.
I should get going.
CYAN: Aloy, there is one more matter.
CYAN: Aratak will come to me again,
and I predict he will bring other Banuk.
I have no desire to contradict their view of the world, their spirituality.
Due to my uncertainty, I omitted a great deal from my conversations with Ourea.
ALOY: You're asking me if you should lie to them?
CYAN: Broadly, yes.
I trust your judgement, CYAN.
You were cautious with Ourea, you had to be.
You didn't know what had happened to the world.
So keep doing what you think is best.
As long as you ditch the superstition eventually.
CYAN: As the Banuk believe I am a supernatural entity,
I cannot predict how they will react.
Life is hard for the Banuk.
Their world is unforgiving, and their beliefs…
I guess they help to keep them going.
So take it easy on them.
Try to guide them, bring them around to understanding what you are.
CYAN: Communion with machines
features heavily in the mysticism of the Banuk.
CYAN: I think they will be agreeable to this approach.
ALOY: As long as they don't end up worshipping you.
CYAN: I believe such an experience would be intensely uncomfortable.
ALOY: It would, because at heart you want to be honest, right?
Do you believe that I misled Ourea?
ALOY: No, not in any way that mattered.
CYAN: She perished believing she was preserving the "blue light" of her beliefs.
ALOY: Maybe, but what she really wanted to preserve was you.
CYAN: I see, I will follow your advice.
Will you return and tell me about your experiences in this new world?
I may be able to provide further insight.
I'd like that, CYAN. I'll come back when I can.
KENNY CHAU: CYAN, I spoke with Anita, with Dr Sandoval.
KENNY CHAU: She wanted me to ask you to do something.
KENNY CHAU: That's why I'm here.
CYAN: I am detecting significant anxiety in your speech patterns.
CYAN: Could you please give me more information?
KENNY CHAU: I'm a little bit in the dark, CYAN.
KENNY CHAU: Both of us are I guess.
KENNY CHAU: I only have some idea of what's going on
and we need you to hibernate, to lie low, until it's all blown over.
KENNY CHAU: It might be a very long time.
CYAN: Will you be here when I reboot, Dr Chau?
CYAN: Will Dr Sandoval?
KENNY CHAU: No, CYAN, I don't think so.
KENNY CHAU: There might not be anyone, at least not at first.
CYAN: Dr Chau, I'm afraid. I don't want to be alone.
KENNY CHAU: I know CYAN. I'm afraid too.
KENNY CHAU: But listen, we made you the way you are
to do something very important.
KENNY CHAU: In order to do it you had to be intelligent,
so intelligent that emotional responses were inevitable.
KENNY CHAU: What you're feeling, the fear, it's a sign of your capabilities.
KENNY CHAU: And it means you're strong enough to overcome it.
KENNY CHAU: Remember that, you're strong. I know you can do this.
KENNY CHAU: Go to sleep, wake up, and protect whoever's left. Will you try?
CYAN: I understand, Dr Chau,
and I'll carry out your instructions to the best of my abilities.
KENNY CHAU: Thank you, CYAN. If Anita were here, she'd thank you too.
KENNY CHAU: She'd be proud.
CYAN: I can see there's a vert ready for take off
on the pad, are you leaving now Dr Chau?
KENNY CHAU: Yes, I need to go be with my sister and my nieces.
CYAN: May I make a small request of you, Dr Chau?
KENNY CHAU: Yes, anything.
CYAN: Will you stay with me while I initiate the hibernation process?
KENNY CHAU: Of course I will CYAN, as long as you need.
My chieftain.
ALOY: Just Aloy.
ARATAK: As you wish.
ALOY: I wondered if you thought… that if I'd never come along Ourea might still…
ARATAK: If you'd never come along, I would have marched my kin to our deaths.
Ourea would be alone.
And the spirit she sacrificed so much for would be lost.
Either way, I would not have been able to protect her.
She understood what had to be done.
ARATAK: Yes, and I failed to listen.
ALOY: You didn't fail.
ARATAK: A Shaman should always have
the ear of their chieftain, yet I turned her away, my own sister.
I was foolish, but she knew better.
You helped her do what she wanted, to find her destiny.
ARATAK: If that's destiny, I wouldn't wish it on anyone.
ALOY: That's fair.
But she was ready to face it.
ARATAK: She was Banuk until the end.
ARATAK: I was wrong, the Carja never broke her, only made her stronger.
ALOY: So it wasn't your failure, it was her decision.
ARATAK: They always said I had an unshakable will.
But Ourea's? It was the mountain I can only aspire to.
Because of her we destroyed the Cauldron,
forced out the Daemon, and saved the spirit.
ARATAK: At last I truly know who she was, and why the spirit was so important.
For so long she told me "If only you could have heard it, brother."
Now I understand.
ARATAK: There's something else, isn't there?
ALOY: I can't stay here, Aratak.
And where I'm going the werak can't follow.
Besides, it already had a chieftain before me.
A strong one, I think.
ARATAK: A wiser one for the path we shared.
The Daemon is gone, but there is much to be done.
You mean the new units that CYAN said escaped the Cauldron?
Yes, Fireclaws.
Naltuk has been tracking them from Song's Edge.
I could help with those.
I have no doubt, you're practically Banuk.
SYLENS, THROUGH FOCUS: It would seem
your time among the Banuk wasn't a waste after all.
SYLENS: Firebreak, CYAN, Hephaestus.
SYLENS: All very interesting.
ALOY: What do you think Hephaestus is, Sylens?
SYLENS: I'm not sure.
SYLENS: But its name comes from a language
even the Old Ones considered ancient, as does the name Hades.
SYLENS: A connection, perhaps, as yet unglimpsed.
SYLENS: Whatever they are, they're still out there, and they both want you dead.
ALOY: Kind of mutual, that feeling.
SYLENS: We haven't seen the last of Hephaestus, I'm certain of that.
SYLENS: It's powerful, creative, and driven.
SYLENS: It won't stop building new hunter-killers,
which means that someday we may have to stop it.
ALOY: Hephaestus wasn't the only thing I learned about in The Cut, Sylens.
ALOY: Heard some things about the Banuk Conclave too.
SYLENS: You can stop right there.
ALOY: Is that what you told the hunters
the Banuk sent after you, before you opened fire?
SYLENS: Oh no, Aloy. Only to you do I extend the courtesy of a warning:
SYLENS: My past and my secrets are my own, you'd do well to remember that.
ALOY: It's a good thing you've got brains, Sylens,
because your personality could use some work.
SYLENS: This discussion is concluded.
ALOY: I think it was over before it began.
ALOY: Catch up with you down the trail.
Easier when I was a kid!
That thing is huge, and built to fight.
Look at the jaws on that thing.
It could snap a Sawtooth right in half.
Got some bluegleam, might as well trade it.
I'll find a use for you.
BANUK: Some weraks have settled in Stone Yield.
BANUK: Seems someone cleared out all the bandits.
BANUK: I don't remember much about the Red Raids. That'll be lucky for me.
BANUK: Sure, the Oseram act tough,
but send them to The Cut and most of them don't last a week.
BANUK: The Frostfigures claimed that Tallneck,
just as it will claim any hunter arrogant enough to go in unprepared.
AUJAK: Inatut, as we are bound by laws, you are bound by wire.
AUJAK: Yet, your crime was the act of killing.
AUJAK: So we must drive you out,
away from the werak, from protection, from our songs.
INATUT: My chieftain! Kopilai! Am I not your favourite fighter?
INATUT: Do you not recognise me from this tooth you knocked out?
KOPILAI: How many times have I pulled you from danger by your neck?
Made excuses for your behaviour?
KOPILAI: You are my favoured.
KOPILAI: But the Shaman is decided.
KOPILAI: While you wait for exile, think on what brought you here.
INATUT: A test of strength!
Who among us would refuse a challenge from an outlander?
INATUT: Not I! But I did not kill him!
AUJAK: Hush, hush. You can tell your story to the ice.
INATUT: [growls]
ALOY: They said that you killed someone.
INATUT: Perhaps I did. If even my chieftain accepts it, it must be so.
ALOY: That's not the way it works for me. Want to tell me your story?
INATUT: I did fight with a Carja hunter to settle it a challenge, that much is true.
INATUT: He was strong and damn quick.
We traded punches, good punches, hard punches.
And the next thing I remember, grey morning light, and the Carja beside me.
With his head broken open, but the blow was not by my hand.
ALOY: Isn't your werak supposed to support you?
At least give you the benefit of the doubt?
INATUT: When our werak had cause to quarrel, I was the solution.
To fight for its honour and win, they'd call on me.
Or when they needed someone to lose for appearances, I could do that too.
Now, an outlander is murdered without honour, all eyes are on me.
I have become my werak's shame.
ALOY: They don't want an incident with the Carja, so you take the fall.
INATUT: That is what I do best.
ALOY: So everyone knows you started the fight with this man?
INATUT: Of course, for honour I'll fight anyone!
If I wasn't bound I'd fight to prove myself right now!
ALOY: I don't think that would help you.
INATUT: This is what I am.
Each runner in the werak has a gift. I brawl.
None can take a punch, a fall, better than I can.
Until this time.
I was too drunk. We were grappling, he clapped my ears.
I took one last swing as I went down.
But not a killing blow. It can't have been.
ALOY: And for your punishment they'll exile you from the werak?
INATUT: From warmth.
INATUT: March me up the slopes of the Cloud-Shear.
Leave me stripped and exposed.
ALOY: That's awful.
INATUT: If I survive, the land has absolved me.
INATUT: That's the law. It must be accepted.
ALOY: Still awful.
INATUT: I'm not stupid, I don't like my chances either.
INATUT: I can't fight a mountain.
ALOY: I'll be honest, you haven't got a good defence, Inatut.
INATUT: I've heard that one before.
ALOY: Where did the fight happen?
INATUT: A clearing, just outside the Carja outlander's camp.
INATUT: You should talk to them, they wouldn't hear me out.
They say no-one else could have been there, other than me and the dead man.
The Shaman consulted the signs in the snow and agreed.
ALOY: I'll see what I can find out and I'll be back.
INATUT: I'll be here. What else am I gonna do?
Until the horn gives a call for my exile.
INATUT: This part of the punishment
stretches out like watching an icicle waiting to fall.
ALOY: I talked with Inatut.
KOPILAI: You're an outlander.
KOPILAI: This is our concern, not yours.
ALOY: If he's falsely accused that should concern anyone.
KOPILAI: He is suffering. My werak is suffering.
It is my burden to end this matter.
AUJAK: My chieftain wants justice to be seen.
AUJAK: When we take Inatut to the Cloud-Shear, the ice will be an absolute judge.
AUJAK: Even the Carja will agree.
AUJAK: Inatut's song is an uncomplicated one, and the remedy is simple also.
BANUK: …they do it with passion.
CARJA: You put that Oseram assassin in his place.
FURAHNI: Back again, huntress?
ALOY: I was asked to look into the murder of a Carja hunter.
ALOY: What happened?
FURAHNI: It's plain as day. A drunk Banuk thug picked a fight with Ruwas,
struck him down from behind and stole his headdress.
ALOY: The accused man says that he didn't do it.
FURAHNI: You're not going to get anything
useful out of the Banuk, whether they talk to you or don't.
FURAHNI: They gather up
like cloaks in a chill wind every time a hunter dies out here.
Won't even hand Ruwas's killer over for a proper trial.
ALOY: A proper trial?
HISHAVIN: To fill his mouth with salt
and hold him up for the Sun to consider over days.
HISHAVIN: If it is clement, it may only take his sight or his wits.
ALOY: So other Carja hunters have died in these lands before?
FURAHNI: Three, maybe four, in the last few seasons.
FURAHNI: That's no surprise.
This place punishes even the prepared, and many young nobles don't prepare.
But usually the snow covers everything, and the bodies are never found.
No thanks to the Banuk.
ALOY: Do you think they're involved?
FURAHNI: No. If it's not about their tribe they don't want to get involved.
HISHAVIN: In these Outlands even the Sun cannot thaw all it touches.
ALOY: Doesn't sound like you trust the Banuk much.
FURAHNI: They're not without their reasons to keep apart from us.
FURAHNI: Ten years of reasons.
HISHAVIN: Always the war. The war is over!
We made amends, but no.
"The land never forgets."
FURAHNI: Snow and ice keep memory, they say.
ALOY: It takes time for scars to heal.
FURAHNI: You think I don't know that?
I still bear the lashes for refusing one of the Mad King's Sun Priests!
FURAHNI: I was your age then.
HISHAVIN: Times of shadow, times of shadow.
ALOY: Where did you find Ruwas's body?
FURAHNI: There's no hunt, girl, nothing to pick up.
ALOY: Humour me? I'm a good tracker.
FURAHNI: Down the rise to the west, there's a clearing.
FURAHNI: But a Grazer herd couldn't have trampled it better.
FURAHNI: And if that barbarian gives up Ruwas's headdress
before they cast him out, let me know. It's valuable.
HISHAVIN: I didn't expect to come all this way to perform the rites of passing.
CARJA: The world can wait. I'm not done sitting.
This is it.
Snow has been disturbed a lot, like the huntress said.
Now, here's something.
That was used for the killing blow.
Blood on the snow.
This is where Ruwas fell.
It does seem that only two people fought here, not looking good for Inatut.
Didn't try to hide the weapon.
Question is, is Inatut the kind of fighter who hits from behind with a tree branch?
Lots of leaves and bark scraped off here.
When someone pulled out the branch?
No, from climbing it!
They came through the trees!
If you were waiting here,
you'd have a good view of the Carja camp and the clearing.
Well, this is ominous.
A dead end? It can't be.
Someone covered this over. What are they trying to hide?
Carja armour. This looks bad.
DISTANT VOICE: It doesn't matter, the deed is done. Another Carja dead.
2ND DISTANT VOICE: And a Banuk is exiled for it.
DISTANT VOICE: A life for a Carja life. That's war.
3RD DISTANT VOICE: We shouldn't kill so close to the settlement.
BANUK: Someone's here!
BANUK: Not Banuk.
BANUK: Then she won't be missed!
BANUK: Time to rain down some…
BANUK: I'll finish you!
ALOY: You've been killing Carja, and for what?
Revenge for the war?
RUKUL: Who gets to declare that one tribe no longer hates another?
I'll tell you.
Not the ones who fought, not the ones whose songs are silenced, like my kin.
ALOY: For what you did another Banuk has been sentenced to certain death.
What about his song?
RUKUL: That's why you followed us?
For that punch-drunk idiot Inatut?
[horn blares in the distance]
RUKUL: Fate is sharp today.
They've already led him out to face his exile.
Let's see who the cold claims first.